Thomas Paine Papers ca.1692-1921 Mss.B.P165
American Philosophical Society
Colonel Richard Gimbel Collection of Thomas Paine Papers
1692 - Circa 1921
Mss.B.P165
American Philosophical Society
0.75 Linear feet 176 items
An important 18th century radical republican theorist and political writer, Thomas Paine was a leading figure in the American Revolution. Despite his humble beginnings and lack of formal education, his reasoned and persuasive writings not only influenced nascent American republican ideology, but profoundly affected the perception of government in England and France as well. His three most influential works are Common Sense (1776), The Rights of Man (1791-1792), and The Age of Reason (1794, 1795, 1807). The Richard Gimbel Collection is a heterogeneous mix of items connected only by the fact that they were all collected by Gimbel (1898-1970) and that most were written by, to, or about the revolutionary Paine. Of primary importance are the approximately sixty-five letters or manuscripts in Paine's own hand, including Paine's 1776 manuscript notes for Common Sense, his letter of January 10, 1781, in which he takes leave of his former commanding officer, Nathanael Greene, and his January 6, 1789 letter to Kitty Nicholson Few, in which he writes of his view of matrimony and other personal matters. The collection includes a series of correspondence between Thomas Paine and Samuel Adams, which were originally marked "forgeries," these appear instead simply to be the letters of two men bearing famous names.
Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809
Naval History Note
The Paine Papers contain at least one item which may be of interest to naval historians:
Jefferson, Thomas. Letter to Thomas Paine. 1788 July 28. Discusses a battle between Admiral Paul Jones and the Prince of Nassau on the 18th of June, the "forerunner of the great decissive action... which took place on the 26th..." Mentions also a "less bloody war" between the Pope and the King of Naples. 4 pages.
Early American History Note
The Thomas Paine Collection is a very rich and diverse collection. Much of the early material is from Paine to others. The later material contains significant documents that Richard Gimbel Collected from the early national period (after 1800) that do not involve Paine but may be of interest to researchers of that period. Included in the documents are notes on Common Sense, letters on courtship and love, the American Revolution, and letters relating to his time in France after the Revolution.
Paine’s letters provide insight into his early life in America and his role in various aspects of the American Revolution, including serving under Nathanael Greene and later operating as a polemicist writing attacks on Rhode Island’s rejection of a nationwide tax in 1782. His letters occasionally touch upon his own views on politics and the new nation. Many of these letters have been transcribed.
Later letters show Paine’s involvement in engineering projects, especially the design and construction of an iron bridge across the Schuylkill, and document his travels through Europe. There is also a long letter to Edmund Burke written in 1788 when Paine was in Paris. The letter discusses the state of affairs on the Continent and how they may relate to England. There is also a letter from Paine while imprisoned in Paris in 1795 to George Washington accusing him of abandoning him, which complements a letter in the Richard Henry Lee Collection in which Washington offered his support for Paine in 1784.
Two manuscript essays are also part of the collection. One is a copy of Common Sense, written after its publication, possibly in England in preparation for publication, and the other is a copy of an unpublished tract attacking Pain’s The Decline and Fall of the English System of Finance.
Finally, there are documents relating to collecting Paine memorabilia and his historical significance, including a letter from Thomas Edison and a record of Paine’s last moments.
The Collection also contains a series of significant letters relating to early national politics and international events. Included in this material are letters dealing with 19th century British politics. There are letters from Thomas Paine to Samuel Adams (although these are not letters from the Thomas Paine and Samuel Adams, it is likely that the Dr. Samuel Adams in these letters was the son of the well-known Massachusetts revolutionary. Dr. Samuel Adams fought in the war and died in 1788.). The letters from this other Paine and Adams are content rich and include discussions of politics, local divisions caused by the imperial crisis, news of the war, and personal matters, including the death of Paine’s wife and reports of the death of Adams’ child in 1782. The letters are written by Paine based in Eastham and then Desert Island, Maine are addressed to Adams based possibly in Truro, Milton, Ipswich, and then possibly serving in the Continental Army. If the Dr. Samuel Adams is the son of Samuel Adams, then this collection complements the large collection of letters the Sol Feinstone Collection has from Samuel Adams Jr. to his wife. Interestingly, these letters go beyond when Samuel Adams Jr. is said to have died. It is quite possible that the Samuel Adams in this correspondence and the Feinstone Collection is another doctor from the Boston area who served in the Continental Army.
Other Finding Aids note
Stephans, Hildegard, compiler, The Thomas Paine Collection of Richard Gimbel in the Library of the American Philosophical Society. Scholarly Resources, 1976. Call no.: 012 P16a
Related Archival Materials note
The Printed Materials Department of the APS Library includes numerous copies of all of Paine's major titles, most of his minor titles, and dozens of newspapers and other works inspired by Paine and his political philosophy. This collection includes everything from first printings of first editions to miscellaneous later editions, foreign language editions, and works on Paine. For further information on Paine's published writings held by the APS, please consult the work cited below.
The Library also houses an extensive collection of political cartoons relating to Painite radicalism and the conservative response. Dating primarily from the period 1792-1805, and printed mostly in England, these include satirical prints by Gilray and Sayre, among many others.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Bequest of Col. Richard Gimbel, 1971.
Scope and Contents note
This eclectic collection was assembled by Richard Gimbel, whose extensive printed collection on Paine is also at the APS (see guidebook cited in "References" below). The manuscripts collection includes approximately sixty-three letters and documents written by Paine, as well as items written to him or related to him. They center on his life in America after 1774 and his years in England and France after 1781. There is much discussion of political matters (American, English, and French), references to his interest in iron bridges, and comments on his writings as well as his personal life (see his letter to Kitty Few). Significant correspondents include John Bayard, Edmund Burke, De Witt Clinton, Kitty Nicholson Few, Abiel Foster, Nathanael Greene, John Hall, Thomas Jefferson, Henry Laurens, James Madison, Thomas Mifflin, James Monroe, Robert Morris, David Rittenhouse, George Washington, and Benjamin West. Correspondence not directly linked to Paine include letters by Moncure D. Conway and Thomas A. Edison. There are also some accounts, receipts, and verses by Paine (one poem concerns General Wolfe), and other writings, such as fragments of his 1776 outline for Common Sense.
Also included in the collection are approximately sixty-five contemporary documents relating to Paine and many miscellaneous items assembled by Gimbel. These include: an interesting series of letters of William Cobbett concerning politics and personal matters (ca. 1798-1834), with a manuscript of his address before 30,000 Irish concerning British-Irish relations, 18 September 1834; a James Monroe letter of 1 November 1794 written to the French Committee of Public Safety on behalf of the imprisoned Paine; and an anonymous manuscript (ca. 1796) replying to Paine's Decline and Fall of the English System of Finance. Twenty-nine manuscript items pulled from Colonel Gimbel's book collection include: a series of letters to Archibald McIntire, et al. concerning New York State lotteries (ca. 1806-1821); numerous writings of one Grant Thornburn, including his, "Reminiscences of New York in 1794," and a historical account of the first use of slate roofs and slate nails in America (New York City, 1794). There is also a small group of documents (ca. 1779-1806) relating to the Bridge Company of Philadelphia, which was set up to erect a permanent bridge over the Schuylkill River (the officers of the company were: Thomas P. Cope, Henry Drinker, and Thomas Parke).
The balance of the collection is a series of twenty-four letters (1775-1793) from Thomas Paine of Eastham and Mount Desert Island to Dr. Samuel Adams. Originally marked "forgeries," these appear instead simply to be the letters of two men bearing famous names.
The collection is divided into two series: Series I Paine Material which contains the correspondence to and from Thomas Paine, as well as manuscripts written by him; and Series II MiscellaneousMaterial which is comprised of the material written about Paine. Series II also contains the Samuel Adams correspondence. Both series are arranged chronologically
Biographical/Historical note
Thomas Paine was one of the foremost political philosophers of the 18th century. His ideas influenced the courses of both the American Revolution and the French Revolution and are still of significance today. His tragic life was partly the result of his status as a man far ahead of his time.
Paine was born January 29, 1737 in Thetford, Norfolk, England, to a Quaker corset-maker and his Anglican.wife. He remained in poverty throughout his life. He was married twice: to Mary Lambert in 1759 (she died within a year), and to Elizabeth Olive in 1771 (they separated in 1774). A hint of the course his life would later take came in 1772, when he was fired from his job as an excise officer for publishing a document advocating higher wages as a method for curtailing corruption in government service.
Paine became acquainted with Benjamin Franklin while in London. Franklin was impressed by Paine's mind and may have seen something of himself in the younger man. Both came from humble origins and were largely self-educated, but showed a broad intellectual understanding and a passionate engagement in life. Paine immigrated to Philadelphia in 1774, armed with letters of introduction from Franklin. He became an editor at the Pennsylvania Magazine and began to anonymously publish his own essays and poetry. One of his earliest pieces was "African Slavery in America" (1775), one of the first and most influential abolitionist writings in America.
His great tour de force was the 50-page pamphlet Common Sense, which was published anonymously on January 10, 1776. It sold more than 500,000 copies in a few months. Its central thesis, that common sense dictates that the colonies derive no benefit from their association with Great Britain and therefore should become independent, helped to fan the flames of revolution that led to the drafting of the Declaration of Independence six months later. Between 1776 and 1783 he issued a series of pamphlets under the title The American Crisis. General George Washington ordered Paine's works (which included the famous line, "These are the times that try men's souls") to be read to the flagging American troops as an inspiration to presevere in their cause. Paine served briefly in the colonial army under the command of General Nathanael Greene. In 1777, he was appointed secretary of the Committee of Foreign Affairs by the Second Continental Congress. He lost that position in 1779 due to political disputes, but later became the clerk of the Pennsylvania legislature. In 1785, he was elected to the American Philosophical Society.
Financial and political difficulties led Paine to return to England in 1787. There he published his Rights of Man in two parts, in 1791 and 1792. This eloquent refutation of Edmund Burke's critical Reflections Upon the French Revolution sold a million and a half copies before it was supressed. Paine's stance against monarchy and for a republican form of government caused him to be tried for treason by the British government in 1792. Already on his way to France when the order for his arrest was issued, Paine still managed to remain embroiled in controversy. He took his seat in the French National Convention, but offended Robespierre by favoring exile, rather than execution, for King Louis XVI. He was imprisoned from December 1793 to November 1794, during which time Part I of his The Age of Reason was published. Part II was published in 1795, and part of Part III in 1807. In this work he severely criticized organized religion, but his words were widely misinterpreted as a defense of atheism. He lost many friends as a result.
In 1802 President Thomas Jefferson helped him return to the United States, and he went to live on his farm in New Rochelle, NY. Instead of being remembered for his contributions to the revolution, Paine found he was feared for his radical ideas and infamous as the world's greatest infidel. His final days were marred by poverty, poor health, and enmity. He died on June 8, 1809 in New York City and was buried on his farm after sacred ground was refused. Ten years later, journalist William Cobbett disinterned his remains and brought them to England with the intention of building a proper monument to this great thinker. The curse of Paine's unhappy life followed him even after death, as Cobbett's vision was never realized and Paine's remains were lost.
Adams, Samuel; Bayard, John Bubenheim, 1738-1807; Bridge Company of Philadelphia; Burke, Edmund, 1729-1797; Clinton, George, 1739-1812; Clymer, George, 1734-1813; Cobbett, William, 1763-1835; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907; Cope, Thomas Pim, 1768-1854; Drinker, Henry; Edison, Thomas A., (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931; Few, Kitty Nicholson; Foster, Abiel, 1735-1806; Greene, Nathanael, 1742-1786; Hall, John; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Laurens, Henry, 1724-1792; Madison, James, 1751-1836; McIntere, Archibald; Mifflin, Thomas, 1744-1800; Monroe, James, 1758-1831; Morris, Robert, 1734-1806; Parke, Thomas, 1749-1835; Rittenhouse, David, 1732-1796; Thorburn, Grant, 1773-1863; Washington, George, 1732-1799; West, Benjamin, 1738-1820; Wolfe, James, 1727-1759; American Revolution; Americans Abroad; Bridges--18th century; Colonial Politics; Early National Politics; Engineering; France--Politics and government--1789-1815; General Correspondence; Great Britain--Politics and government--1789-1820; International Affairs; Ireland--Foreign relations; Lotteries--New York (State); Manuscript Essays; Marriage and Family Life; New York (N.Y.)--Description and travel--18th century; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809; Printing and Publishing; Roofing, Slate; Schuylkill River Bridge; Science and Technology; United States--Politics and government--Revolution, 1775-1783
- Series I. Paine Material, 1775-1808
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains correspondence to and from Thomas Paine. There are also manuscript copies of documents written by Paine.
  - ALS to John Bayard, 1738-1807, 1777 October 30; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
  - ALS to Henry Laurens, 1724-1792, 1778 April 11; 3p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
  - ALS to Henry Laurens, 1724-1792, 1779 January 9; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
  - ALS to Pennsylvania. Supreme Executive Council, 1779 October 11; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
  - ADS to David Rittenhouse, 1732-1796, 1779 November 27; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
    Order to Rittenhouse to John Bayard.
  - ADS to Thomas Paine, 1781 January 9; 2p.; Frederick A. Muhlenberg, 1750-1801 ( Speaker of the General Assembly) (Box 1)
    Order for payment to Thomas Paine for "Service as Clerk of the general Assembly..." On reverse: order for payment to Thomas Paine signed by William Moore, Vice President of the General Assembly, and David Rittenhouse, Treasurer, dated 1781, January 9.
  - ALS to Nathaniel Greene, 1740-1786, 1781 January 10; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
    About Henry Laurens' appointment as "Envoy Extraordinary to France," Paine's subsequent appointment as his secretary, and leaving America for France.
  - ALS to Nathaniel Greene, 1740-1786, 1781 September 10; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
    About Paine's return to America and his appreciation to Greene for his "enterprise, address, management and success to the southward..."
  - ALS to Robert Morris, 1734-1806, 1782 November 28; 4p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
  - ALS to Honorable Clarke, Congress, 1783 June 24; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
    Request for the "Committee" to allow Paine to submit in writing "a detail of circumstances" before making a report.
  - ALS to Robert Morriss, 1734-1806, 1783 October 14; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
    Regarding the "Treaty and Treaty of Commerce."
  - ALS to John Hall, 1783? October; 3p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
    About the sent "battau" and Paine's planned date of arrival to New York.
  - ALS to George Clinton, 1739-1812, 1783 December 19; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
  - ALS to Thomas Mifflin, 1744-1800, 1785 December 19; 3p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
    A reminder to Mifflin about due compensation for "eminent Services rendered to America, during the late revolution..."
  - ALS to Henry Claypole, 1786 March 22; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
    An indignant letter from Paine suggesting that Claypole was negligent in not printing the piece that Paine had sent.
  - ALS to John Hall, 1786 September 22; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
    About living arrangements.
  - ALS to George Clymer, 1734-1813, 1786 December 13; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
    About debates and Paine's "Model."
  - ALS to Dr. Samuel Adams, 1787 January 21; 3p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
  - ALS to "Messieurs", 1787 May 24- 1787 July 21; 2 items (5p).; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
    Letter introducing Paine's "model of the construction of an American bridge." Enclosed is an "Extract from the Minutes of the Assembly of Pennsylvania, May 24, 1787. The 3-page AD is a "Committee" (favorable) report on Paine's bridge model.
  - ALS to Lewis Morris, 1726-1798, 1788 May 4; 4p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
  - ALS to unknown, 1788 July 11; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
  - ALS to Benjamin West, 1746-1817, 1788 July 13; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
    Short letter mentioning poor health, a new election for Westminster, and a trip to"Wilkinson's Iron Works in Shropshire.
  - ALS extract to Thomas Paine, 1788 July 28; 4p.; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826 (Box 1)
    About a battle between Admiral Paul Jones and the Prince of Nassau on the 18th of June, the "forerunner of the great decissive action... which took place on the 26th..." Mentions also a "less bloody war between the Pope and the King of Naples..."
  - ALS to Edmund Burke, 1729-1797, 1788 August 7; 10p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
  - AL to Kitty Nicholson Few, 1789 January 6-7; 10p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
    A very sentimental letter inspired by Few's recent marriage.
  - ALS to Sam Walker and Co., 1791 August 30; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
  - ALS to John Hall, 1792 February 16; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
  - Copy of ALS to Thomas Paine, 1737-1809., 1792 May 6; 2p.; Washington, George, 1732-1799. In French. (Box 1)
    Washington thanks Paine for copies of "Rights of Man," and other works.
  - ALS to Thomas Paine, 1737-1809, 1792 May 30; 1p.; Oswald, Eleazer, 1755-1795 (Box 1)
    About meeting to discuss politcal situation in France.
  - ALS to Thomas Paine, 1737-1808, 1795 February 7; 4p.; Ackers, James, 1756?-1827 (Box 1)
    About the House of Commons, "procuring and fabricating signatures on petitions," and the Bulls Head Party.
  - ALS to Citoyen Pelet, 1795 February 27; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
    About a future publication and a letter of introduction for a young Englishwomen needing a passport.
  - ALS and ALSCy in French to Pelet, 1795 February 27; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
    Two versions (one in French) of an appeal for a passport to help "a harmless unoffending woman."
  - ALS to George Washington, 1732-1799, 1795 September 20; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
    A scathing letter in which Paine accuses Washington of treachery.
  - ALS to James Monroe, 1758-1831, ca. 1795; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
  - AMS to Stephen Thorn and George Barnes, 1796 December 10; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
    Deed of gift to Stephen Thorn and George Barnes for the "Letter from Thomas Paine to George Washington..."
  - ALS to Paul Francois Jean Nicolas, comte de Barras, 1755-1829, 1797 January 3; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
    Recommending Captain Blackwell, "who wishes to be sent to Ireland...to assist in making his native oppressed country free."
  - Ams to Nathan Haley, 1799 August 31; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 1)
  - ALS to Skipwith, 1801 February 3; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Skipwith, 1801 September 29; 3p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
    Congratulations and cautionary advice on Skipwith's commission.
  - ALS to Skipwith, 1801 December 14; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to John Fellows, 1805 June 4; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - Ams, 1806 Nov. 13; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
    At the end of this piece,"To a Friend of Peace," appears the note: "This fragment is in the Handwriting of Thomas Paine and was given to me by a person named Clarke who brought it from America. December 1830."
  - ALS to Binney and Ronaldson, 1807 April 8; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
    About politcs and seeking housing.
  - ALS to James Madison, 1751-1836, 1807 May 3; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
    About Paine's imprisonment at the hands of "Robspere" and his subsequent release on "Mr. Monro's reclamation."
  - AMS fragments, 1807 August 21; 4p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
    Last part of "Reply to Cheetham."
  - Ams to Thomas Jefferson, 1743-1826, 1807 August 29; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
    About "a proposed method of firing guns from a gun boat..."
  - Ams, 1807 October 17 (received); 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
    "Thomas Paine's Project for a reform of the Judiciary."
  - ADS, 1808 July 6; 4p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
    Indenture with John Oliver.
  - Fragment of AMS to John Bayard, 1738-1807, n.d.; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
    Addressed to Hon. John Bayard, to be read to the general Assembly.
  - ALS to Henry Claypole, n.d.; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
    Paine accuses Claypole of censorship.
  - AMS to Robert Smith, n.d.; 2p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
    "What is Love?"
  - AMS to Robert Smith, n.d.; 2 items (3p).; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
    Two copies of the same poem, "What is Love?" prefaced with the same introduction, "To Sir Robert Smith, As I will not attempt to rival description of Love, in which you say Love is like paper credit, it has no security; 'with a fool it is wit...'"
  - AL to George Staunton, n.d.; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - ALS to Waterman, n.d.; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)
  - AMS Accidental Reconciliation, From the Castle in the Air to the little Corner of the World", n.d.; 2 items (7p.); Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 2)